American Federation of Labor, Railway Employees Department vs. Union Pacific Railroad Company, Hanson et al. Records 5366
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Federation of Labor Railway Employees Department vs. Union Pacific Railroad Company, Hanson et al. Records
1955- 1956
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
American Federation of Labor
Union Pacific Railroad Company (UP)
Nebraska. Supreme Court
Nebraska, Amicus Curiae
Florida, Amicus Curiae
Mississippi, Amicus Curiae
South Carolina, Amicus Curiae
Virginia, Amicus Curiae
Texas, Amicus Curiae
South Dakota, Amicus Curiae
Utah, Amicus Curiae
5366
0.5 cubic feet
0.5 linear ft.
Records (documents).
This collection consists of judicial opinions, amicus briefs, and a law journal article relating to a case argued before both the Nebraska State Supreme Court and the United States Supreme Court. This was a case designed to determine the constitutionality of the union shop provision of the Railway Labor Act. The union shop provision was amended to the act in 1951 [Section 2, Eleventh]. The case was argued before the Nebraska Supreme Court in July 1955, and in front of the United States Supreme Court in October 1955 [No. 451].
5619744
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
E. Parker, March 31, 2017
EAD encoding:
E. Parker, March 31, 2017
Biographical / Historical
The Railway Labor Act [RLA], which applies to employees of interstate rail and air carriers, was amended in 1951 to add a union shop provision [Section 2, Eleventh]. Prior to 1951, the RLA did not have this clause, but rather specified that union membership could not be a requirement to employment nor were union-dues check-offs allowed. This was to curb the possibility of company controlled labor organizations serving as bargaining agents with themselves at the expense of the employees. By 1951, these company dominated unions were no longer a factor, and after lobbying by railroad labor groups, the above mentioned amendment was added to the RLA, empowering unions to enter into union shop agreements with railroad carriers. The amendment to the RLA reads, in part, that labor organizations "shall be permitted...to make agreements, requiring, as a condition of continued employment, that within 60 days the beginning of such employment all employees shall become members of the labor organization representing their craft or class" [Section 2, Eleventh (a)]. In addition to allowing the union shop, the amendment also explicitly stated that this amendment superseded any laws or statutes passed at the local or state level. However, the amendment did not repeal the prior injunction against union shop; it merely superseded it. This is in contrast to the Taft-Hartley Act, which allows individual states to impose more stringent measures against unions. At the time of the amendment to the RLA, there were eighteen states with right to work laws that outlawed union shop agreements; eleven of these were in the South.
In 1953, Union Pacific Railroad Company [UP] entered into a union shop agreement with sixteen labor unions. The plaintiffs, Robert L. Hanson and other non-union employees of UP, sued the company and the labor unions in a district court in Nebraska to halt the union shop agreement because Nebraska has a right to work clause in its state constitution. The plaintiffs argued that in addition to being unconstitutional under the state constitution, they would suffer irreperable injury by being forced to pay dues, fees, and assessments to an organization they were being compelled to join. Conversely, the unions argued that these employees, dubbed "free riders," enjoyed all the benefits the unions achieved for employees through collective bargaining without paying their share of the costs of conducting those bargaining agreements.
The district court judge issued the injunction and in 1954 found in favor of the plaintiffs. The unions appealed the case to the Supreme Court of Nebraska which, in an opinion written by Justice Adolph Wenke, upheld the lower court's decision. The labor unions then appealled the case to the United States Supreme Court.
The United States Supreme Court found the union shop provision of the RLA constitutional. Justice Douglas wrote in his opinion, "We only hold that the requirement for financial support of the collective-bargaining agency by all who receive the benefits of its work is within the power of Congress under the Commerce Clause."
The complete text of the U.S. Supreme Court's decision may be found here.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1955-1956
Bulk date: 1955
This collection consists of the released opinion of the Supreme Court of Nebraska in the case of Hanson v. Union Pacific Railroad Company [160 Neb. 669, 71 N.W. (2d) 526 (1955)], fourteen amicus briefs filed with the United States Supreme Court by various enitities after the suit was successfully appealed, the brief Robert L. Hanson and his fellow individual appellees filed with the Supreme Court, and an article written by J. A. McClain, Jr., dean of the School of Law of Duke University on the ruling of the Supreme Court.
The opinion of the Nebraska Supreme Court was written by Justice Adolph Wenke and found in favor of the plaintiffs. Amicus briefs were filed by other individuals opposed to union shops, organizations that supported right to work legislation, and individual American states and commonwealths that had right to work laws. The organizations represented in the amicus briefs are the American Farm Bureau Federation, the National Right to Work Committee, the National Association of Manufacturers, the Chamber of Commerce of the United States, and the Southern States Industrial Council. The states and commonwealths who filed amicus briefs are South Carolina, Virginia, Texas, South Dakota, and Utah; Nebraska, Florida, and Mississippi filed their brief jointly.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5378: M.E. Sandsberry, Jr. et al. vs. Gulf Colorado and Santa Fe Railway Company et al. Records
Open and closed shop -- Nebraska; Railroads -- Employees -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions -- United States; Hanson, Robert L., appellee; American Federation of Labor, appellants; American Federation of Labor. Railway Employees Dept., appellants; Union Pacific Railroad Company, appellee; United States. Railway Labor Act
5619744
- Opinion Released by the Nebraska Supreme Court on July 1, 1955 in re Hanson, et al. v. Union Pacific, et al. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Robert L. Hanson, et al., appellees v. Union Pacific Railroad Company, a corporation, appellee, Railway Employees' Department, American Federation of Labor, et al., appellants.
- Brief of the Sandsberry Petitioners as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  October, 1955.
- Brief of Lafayette A Hooser et al employees discharged under union shop contracts on several railroads, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Brief of Robert L. Hanson, et al, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Brief for the States as Amici Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  October, 1955. The States are Nebraska, Florida, and Mississippi.
- Brief for American Farm Bureau Federation as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Brief for Charles L. Bradford et al as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Brief of the State of South Carolina as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Brief of Lindsay Almond Jr. Attorney General of Virginia, as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Brief of the State of Texas as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Brief for the National Right To Work Committee as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Brief of the National Association of Manufacturers of U.S.A. as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Brief for the Chamber of Commerce of the United States as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Brief of the State of South Dakota as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Brief of the Southern States Industrial Council as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Brief for the State of Utah as Amicus Curiae, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- "The Union Shop Amendment: Compulsory 'Freedom" To Join a Union", 1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  by J. A. McClain, Jr., Dean of the School of Law at Duke University. Reprinted from American Bar Association Journal, August 1956.